我们谈谈内存管理
let's talk about memory management
特别是
and specifically
内核的内存管理
memory management as the kernel relates to memory management
回忆一下传统的计算机架构
recall the traditional computer architecture
有一个CPU
we have a CPU
有内存
we have memory
和磁盘有交互
there's some sort of interaction with disk
和网络等等有交互
with a network etc etc
这个到底是什么样子
but what does this really really look like
在电脑里
well in a computer
有一根、两根或更多的内存条
there's one stick or two sticks or have some finest sticks of RAM
但却可能有成百上千个进程
but there can be hundreds and hundreds of processes
每个进程都有一个虚拟内存空间
and each process has a virtual memory space
你们可能对这张基础课程的幻灯片很熟悉
that you might find familiar with this slide from the fundamentals lectures
它实际出自Linux基础：0x03进程加载
from the actually linux process loading lectures now
你现在看起来有点
where you know as you've now seem quite a bit
每个进程都在某处加载了二进制文件
every process has the binary loaded somewhere
在某处加载了库，等等
the libraries loaded somewhere etc etc etc
但是你只有一个物理内存
but again you have only one physical memory
对于非位置无关代码的情况
and you can only have one physical address of 0x400100
你只能有一个0x400100地址
in the case of a non position independent code
那么如何将多个程序加载到内存中
so how would you load multiple programs into memory
且是以一种他们不会互相冲突的方式
in a way that they wouldn't clobber each other
一个解决方案当然是采用位置无关代码
one solution of course position independing code
这就是库用的方法
this is what libraries do
你可以在任何地方加载库
you can load libraries anywhere
他们自己去找好地址
they figure the heck out
但这仍然不能互相隔离开
but that still doesn't give you isolation
一个库很容易就能乱动另一个库
one library can mess with another library pretty easily
所以我们提出了虚拟内存的概念
so we came up with the concept of virtual memory
实际上
and actually
我得记一下
now I have to make a note to myself
以后在这里添加一些历史背景
to add some historical context here
虚拟内存这个概念出现在60年代
virtual memory this concept came out around the 60s
我看到的最早的文献记录提到
is where the literature is that I first started seeing these musings on
嘿，也许我们应该确保一个进程
hey maybe we should make sure that a process
一个进程不能破坏另一个进程的内存空间，等等
one process can't clobber memory space of another process and so forth
虚拟内存为不同进程提供了对物理内存的不同视图
and virtual memory provides views for different processes into physical memory
物理内存是一根长长的RAM棒
the physical memory is one big long stick of RAM
虚拟内存是各进程对物理内存的视图
and the virtual memory is views that every process has into it
内核配合CPU
and the kernel in collaboration with architecture and features of the CPU
维护虚拟地址和物理地址之间的映射关系
maintains mappings between the virtual addresses and the physical addresses
怎么做的呢
so how might you do this
一个简单的方法是说，好吧，嘿
well one easy way is say okay hey
每个进程有，假设4KB的内存
every process gets let's say 4 KB of memory
从0到FFF
0x from 0 to fff
它们的整个虚拟内存空间
and their entire virtual memory space
以某个物理地址为基址，映射到物理内存上
gets mapped in somewhere from some base into physical memory
比如
so you say okay I know that
P1加上0x1000
P1 I just add 0x1000
或者P2加上0x1000
or P2 I just add a 0x1000
就是它在虚拟内存中的位置
and that's where it is in virtual memory
这样地址转换就很简单
and so the translations are easy
进程能跑，等等
the processes work etc etc etc
但如果进程2需要更多内存呢
but then what if process 2 needs more memory
我们的解决方案是
well our solution was hey
我们允许内存
we allow for memory
在进程的虚拟内存空间中，是连续的
continuous memory in the virtual memory space of a process
但在进程的物理内存空间中，可以是不连续的
to be non contiguous in the physical memory space of a process
这里一页占0x1000字节
so on this page by page basis of 0x1000 bytes
在物理内存中，都是连续的
everything is contiguous in physical memory
但是在虚拟内存中每个页面
but in virtual memory each page
抱歉
sorry
在物理和虚拟内存中，对于一个页面的0x1000字节，所有内容都是连续的
everything's contiguous for this 0x1000 bytes for one page in both physical and virtual memory
但对于连续的虚拟内存页
but continuous virtual pages
可能完全随机地放在可用的物理内存中
might be completely randomly set aside in physical memory as available
我们必须这样做
and we had to do this
因为如你所见
because as you saw here
进程2申请更多内存
process two requested more memory
而它正好挨着进程3的内存
and it was right up against the memory of process 3
所以我们无法让它保持连续
so we couldn't just keep it continuous
我们可以移走进程3的内存
we could have moved process 3
再扩展进程2的内存
expanded process 2
但这很耗时
but that's expensive
所有这些内存整块复制之类的都很耗时
all of this memory moving and stuff
不太好
just not not so great
所以现在我们有这个问题
so now we have this problem
我们必须要记录这些鬼东西
where hey we have to track all of this shit
我们得弄清楚
we have to figure out hey hey
进程1的第1页实际上在物理内存中的这里
page 1 of process 1 is actually here in physical memory
进程1的第二页在这里，等等
page 2 of process 1 is here and so forth
很久以前
and so sometime way back when lost in the historical record
我们接到消息称，有人实现了1级页表
we have a report that someone's done with level 1
我们一起看看
let's see
（音量警告）
有人实现了1级页表，恭喜
boom one solve of level 1 congratulations
（总部？）
HQ(headquarter？)
大惊喜
big surprise
好了，比赛开始了
all right the race is on
很久以前
sometime way back when
甚至还在进程出现时
in the birth of the process even
我们就创造了页表的概念
we created this concept of page tables
思路是
and the idea is
对于每个内存页
for every page
它是一个连续的，4KB的内存块
which is a contiguous chunk of 0x1000 of 4,096 bytes 4 KB
我们在页表中，记录
we track in the page table
内存页的物理地址
the physical address of that page
一个页表
and each page table
因为现在开始，我们用页讨论内存
because we have now started talking about memory in terms of pages
实际上，我们一直在用页讨论内存
and we have actually been talking about memory in terms of pages this whole time
这并非偶然
and that's not an accident
每个页表有512个记录项
each page table holds 512 entries
为什么
why
因为4KB除以8B（页表占一页）
because 0x1000 divided by 8
现在每个地址8字节，64位
right now we have 8 byte addresses 64 bit
结果是512
is 512
这就是页表能容纳的记录项数目
that's how many entries fit in one page
页表占用一页，既有经验上的原因
and a page table takes up one page for spiritual reasons
也是出于性能上的考量
but also implementation performance reasons
总之，一个页表能记录512个页
so this allows us to hold 512 pages in the page table
每个页面包含4KB内存
each page contains 0x1,000 4KB of memory
总共加起来有2MB
that adds up to 2 MB
每个进程，用一个页表，可管2MB内存
so now each process with a page table can have 2MB of memory
这2MB内存，在物理内存中，不必连续
and this memory doesn't have to be contiguous in the physical memory
但它在虚拟地址空间中是连续的
but it's contiguous in the virtual address space
酷
amazing
但有一个问题
but there's a problem
我们需要的内存，当然超过了2MB
of course we need more than 2 MB of RAM
光libc就超过2MB内存了
libc needs more than 2 MB of RAM
比如
like you know
就算只有一个helloworld
even if we just have a hello world
它占用的内存都超2MB了
that has a memory footprint nowadays of more than 2 MB of RAM
不是一直这样的
it wasn't always like that
我们以前很注意使用的内存大小
we used to be careful with our memory
但现在不的了
but now we're not
这都怪康纳
and I blame Connor
不，我只是开个玩笑
no I'm just kidding
我们肯定需要2MB以上的内存
but we definitely need more than 2MB of RAM come on
Linux内核本身就占用了大约700MB的内存
the Linux kernel itself takes up like 700 MB of RAM
这是荒谬的
it's ridiculous
可能不总是，全都加载在内存中，等等
I mean that's probably not all loaded into memory at all times etc etc etc
但若你看一下未压缩的VMLinux映像
but if you look at the uncompressed VMLinux image
它非常大
it's pretty big
Chrome也很庞大
Chrome is gigantic too
别让我打开Chrome
don't get me starting Chrome
显然我们需要不止2MB
obviously we need more than 2MB
那么有着无穷智慧的架构设计师做了什么呢
so what did the architecture designers in their infinite wisdom do
他们说，这个页表
well they said hey well this page table thing
效果很好
works pretty well
要是在页表里放页表呢
what if I put a page table in your page table
这样就可以在内存页中分页
so you could page while you page
我们就这么做了
we did exactly that
我们创造了页目录的概念（PD）
we created the concept of page directories
我说的“我们”是指社会
and by we I mean society
页目录PD中的记录项指向页表PT
and page directories have entries that point to page tables
页表PT中记录着页的物理地址
that have entries that point to pages in physical memory
顺便说一下，这个指针是页表的物理地址
and this pointer is the physical address of a page table by the way
这样就可以很好地解决了（虚拟内存不足的问题）
so it can just all be nicely resolved
一个页目录包含512个记录项
a page directory contains 512 page directory entries
因为每一项占8字节
because every entry is 8 bytes and
一个页目录占一页
a page directory takes up one page
因为内存是以页来管理的
because memories managed in pages
这意味着
which means
512 * 2MB = 1GB的可寻址虚拟内存
512 times 2 MB is 1 GB of addressable virtual memory
谁还需要更多呢
who would need anything more
这样会有一些固定开销
this has some overhead
每2MB的内存，我们需要一个页表
for every 2 MB of memory we need a page table
页表占用一页
with Page Table takes up a page
所以每2MB内存需要4KB
so it takes 4 KB for every 2 MB of RAM
另外，页目录本身占用4KB
plus it takes 4 KB for the page directory itself
这有点不舒服
that starts getting a little bit uncomfortable
每1GB需要2MB左右的固定内存开销
that's like 2 MB of memory overhead for every GB
不夸张，但不舒服
not insane but people get nervous
于是他们说，可以用一个特殊的标志来减少一点开销
so they said okay hey we can reduce the overhead a little bit with a special flag
能注意到，地址末尾都是000
and you'll notice all of these last few bytes are all zeros
因为我们是以页为单位
because of course we're addressing pages
所以每个记录项有12位可用于标记
so there's plenty of space 12 bits per entry here for flags
通过设置一个标记
by setting a flag
页目录的记录项
a page directory entry
可以不再指向页表
instead of referring to a page table
而是指向一个所谓的大页
can just refer to what's called a large page
2MB的连续物理内存
2 MB of contiguous physical memory
酷
cool
现在我们解决了这个问题
so now we solve the problem
虚拟内存增加到1GB
we can go up to 1 GB
如果你生活在2000年，那会很棒
which would be great if you were living in the year 2000
比如《杰森一家》
like the Jetsons
杰森一家可能只有页目录
the Jetsons probably only had page directories
但我们不是杰森一家
but we are not the Jetsons
不管我们有多想成为杰森一家
no matter how much we want to be the Jetsons
我们不能
we can't
我们甚至没有会飞的汽车
we don't even have flying cars
也许我们有飞行汽车的话
maybe we have flying cars
可能放入1GB内存就够
we could fit into a GB of RAM
但我们没有会飞的汽车
but we don't have flying cars
所以
so instead
我们在PD里放PD
we put a page directory in your page directory
所以你可以分页，分页再分页
so you could page while you page while you page
boom
我们创建了一个页目录页表PDPT
we created a page directory page table
我说的“我们”是指社会
and by we i mean Society again
它包含512个PD指针
that contains 512 page directory pointers
总共512GB的可寻址内存
addressing a total of 512 GBs of RAM
当然，这有大量的固定开销
now of course this has insane amounts of overhead
每一个
every
哦，等一下
oh one second
让我
let me
不，不是
no not yeah
每个PD有开销
every page directory represents overhead
每个PT有开销等等
and every page table represents overhead and so forth
但如果看百分比，那就微不足道了
but if it's percentage wise it's minuscule
但人们还是说
but people still said okay
如果你对这些开销感到不舒服
well hey if you're nervous about that overhead
别担心
don't worry
通过在PDPT的记录项中，设置特殊标志
by setting a special flag in the page directory page table entry
它可以指向一个巨页
it can refer to what's called a huge page
从大页（2MB）到现在的巨页（1GB）
we went from large page now to huge page
它是1 GB的连续内存空间
which is a 1 GB continuous space of memory
而不再指向PD
instead of a page directory
很酷
cool very cool
正如有人提到的
as someone mentioned
512GB可能够在Chrome中打开第二个标签页了
512 GBs might now be enough to open a second tab in Chrome
但如果你想打开第三个呢
but what if you want to open a third tab
就完了
you're fucked
在原来PDPT的时代
in the old days of page directory page tables
你就完蛋了
you're screwed
你要再打开另一个标签页呢
how are you gonna open another tab
人们说，好吧，你想要更多的内存
well people said okay you want more RAM
你想要更多的内存
you want more RAM
那就给你更多的内存
you can have more RAM
我们把
we're going to put
PDPT放到PDPT中
a page directory page table in your page directory page table
你就可以分页、分页、分页再分页
so you can page while you page while you page while you page
这把我们带到了现代世界的四级分页
and this brings us to the modern world of four levels of paging structures
这创建了PML4
that created the page map level 4
其中记录了512个PDPT
which contains 512 pdpt entries
每个记录项指向一个PDPT
which point to a page directory page table
PDPT中记录着PD
which point to page directories
PD再记录着PT
which point to page tables
让我们现在，理论上可以处理256TB的内存
allowing us to address a theoretical 256 TB of RAM now
我不知道是否有256TB内存的电脑
I'm not aware if computers that have 256 TB of RAM
但你可以在亚马逊上买到
but you can get RAM computers from Amazon
有好几TB内存的电脑
that have multiple TB of RAM
所以这不仅仅是理论上
so this isn't just theoretical
这已经在实践中有用了
this is used in practice
这很重要
it's important stuff
如果你仔细想想
if you think about it
现在看起来有点高的内存
and think about some amount of storage space that seems a little high
比如256TB
like 256 TB
可能在十年内
probably in a decade
将变成有一点点高
that will be an amount of memory RAM that seems just a little high
20年内，将变成有点低了
and two decades is gonna be an amount of RAM that seems low
曾经就是这样的
and that's how it was before
以前1GB的内存看起来很疯狂
at some point a GB of RAM seemed like insanity
在Yan高中时
in high school
有一阵经济上的
there was a crazy economical
一个疯狂的情况，内存条变得很便宜
like a crazy situation where RAM became insanely cheap
我买了1GB
I bought a GB
我为家里的计算机，买了好几条512MB的内存条
I bought GBs of RAM in 512MB sticks for all the computers in my family
我给主工作站装了1.5GB内存，这很疯狂
and I loaded my main workstation with 1.5 GBs of RAM which was insane
完了，Windows 98无法开机
and Windows 98 refused to boot
想想看
so think about that
我不知道有Mac电脑支持上TB的内存
I didn't know that you could get TB of RAM in the Mac
2040年的mac Pro
only the 2040 mac Pro
是的，实话
yes exactly
好的
so okay anyways
这真的非常令人沮丧
so yeah that was really actually very frustrating
因为Linux运行得很好
because Linux worked just fine
但突然，我就不能切到windows上玩游戏了
but suddenly I couldn't play games anymore
所以我最后把内存降到了768MB
so I ended up actually downgrading to 768 mags of RAM
这是当时windows在我电脑上支持的最大内存
which was the most that Windows could take on my hardware
这真的很烦人
it was really annoying
总之，这就是现代世界
anyway so this is the modern world
这就是你们生活在的世界
this is the world you all live in
是PML4的世界
is the world of PML4
更糟糕的是，我马上就会讲到
and it gets even worse but I'll get to that in a second
PML4非常棒
so PML level4 is pretty awesome
这个
what does this
我们是如何索引到这些PT上的
how do we actually index into all of these tables
虚拟地址到底怎么用
what does a virtual address actually do
这里有个虚拟地址
so I put this virtual address
这是cat /proc/self/maps时，看到的栈地址
this is a stack address when I did cat /proc/self/maps
就是个栈地址
just some some stack address
我们来看看它是如何
let's take a look at how it actually gets translated
转换成物理地址的
into a physical address
我们取12位作为页内偏移（英文口误，非PT）
we take 12 bits as an index into the page table
然后每次取9位
and then 9 bits at a time
表示从0到512
from 0 to 512
作为四级分页的，各级别的索引
as indexes into the different levels of the 4 level paging structure
第一个9位
the first 9 bits
最左边的9位
the left most 9 bits here
是PML4中的索引
are an index into the PML4
到这里
into here
接下来的9位
then the next 9 bits
是PDPT中的索引
are an index into the PDPT
用来选择PD
to select the PD
再接下来的9位是PD中的索引
the next 9 bits are an index into the PD
用来选择PT
to select the PT
即页表
the page table
再下面的9位是PT中的索引
and then the next 9 bits are an index into the page table
用来选择实际内存页
to select the actual page
接下来的12位是页内偏移
and then the next 12 bits are an index into the page
从0到0xFFF
from 0 to 0xFFF
所以当你在程序中访问内存时
so when you access some memory in your program
mov RBX，解引用RBX
mov rax, dereference RBX
这实际上解引用了4次
this actually does 4 different memory dereferences
才拿到实际的内存页
to bring you the actual page
再做最终的解引用
and let you do that dereference
现在回想一下进程是隔离开的
now recall that processes are isolated
所以事情变得更疯狂了
so it gets even crazier
因为你猜怎么着
because hey guess what
每个虚拟地址空间
each virtual address space
每个进程都有自己的PML4
each process has its own PML4
那么如何指定PML4的位置呢
so how do you actually specify where the PML4 is
因为目前有了这么个链条
because so far we've had this circular thing
PT在哪里
because where the PT is
是由PD项指定的
is specified by the PD entry
PD在哪里?
where the PD is
是由PDPT项指定的
is specified by the pdpt entry
PDPT在哪里
where the pdpt is
是由PML4项指定的
is specified by the PML4 entry
PML4在哪
where's the PML4
这是由寄存器指定的
well that is specified by a register
称为CR3寄存器
called the CR3 register
它是一个特殊寄存器
it is a special register
CR表示控制寄存器
controlled register that's what CR stands for
它只能在0环中访问
only accessible in ring 0
我在内核课上提到过
I've mentioned it in the kernel lecture
内核的第一节课
one of the earlier kernel lectures
但现在你能理解它是怎么用的了
but now you know in depth how it's used
还有其他控制寄存器
there are other control registers
其中一些设置了处理器选项
some of them set processor options
其中一些被用于其他疯狂的事情
some of them are used for other crazy things
x86中有很多疯狂的东西
there's a lot of craziness in x86
这是难以置信的
it's incredible
我学到了很多
I learned quite a lot of it
去年专门为defcon创建了一个虚拟化相关的题目
specifically to create a defcon challenge last year for virtualization
我马上就会讲到
which I'll talk about in a second
如果你想隔离开
now so what if you want to isolate
不是说进程，而是虚拟机
not processes but virtual machines
因为你现在正在运行虚拟机
because you're running virtual machines right now
用的方式不同
in actually different ways
对于模拟器，这并不适用
in emulation so this doesn't apply
但当你在电脑上运行虚拟机时
but when you run virtual machines on your computer
通常是虚拟化
typically you're virtualizing
而不是在模拟
you're not emulating
如何隔离虚拟机
how do you isolate virtual machines
每个虚拟机中的内核
where every kernel in those virtual machines
都以为自己可以直接访问物理内存
assumes that it has direct access to physical memory
你可以在虚拟机中运行DOS
you can run DOS in a virtual machine
DOS其实什么都不知道
DOS doesn't know anything really
DOS很诚实
DOS was honest
它就是让你运行你的游戏
it just let you run your games
不碍事
and didn't get in the way
现在你强迫它在Windows 11中运行
and now you're forcing it to run inside Windows 11
或者更糟Mac OS，甚至是Linux
or worse Mac OS or even worse Linux
这很疯狂
it's insanity
那么会发生什么?
so what happens
好吧
well hey
你在页表之上，放了一个扩展页表
you put an extended page table on top of your page table
所以你有一个4级的
so you have a 4 level
一个完整的，额外的，4级页表
an entire additional 4 level translation table
它用于将你虚拟机中的物理地址
that is used to translate guest physical addresses in your virtual machine
转换为宿主机的物理地址
into host physical addresses in your virtual machine
这太他妈疯狂了
and it's just fucking nuts
boom
等一下
actually one second
我们回退2张ppt
let's back up two slides
我忘说一件事
I forgot to mention one thing
这个虚拟地址
this virtual address
12位，9位，9位，9位，9位
12 bits 9 bits 9 bits 9 bits 9 bits
加起来是48位
that adds up to 48 bits
这意味着即使在64位架构上
that means that even on a 64 bit architecture
在当前的设计下，你只能用
you can only address with this current design
他们以后可以引入5级
hey they can introduce a level 5 later
但以目前的设计
but with the current design
你只能用48位的内存
you can only address 48 bits of memory
所有的指针都必须在这48位内
and your pointers all have to be contained in these 48 bits
架构上不支持处理高于48位的内存
there's just no architectural way to address memory higher than 48 bits
这里所有的位
all bits here
在你解引用时，必须要么全0，要么全1
have to either be all 0 or all 1 when you do a dereference
如果它们都是1
and if they're all 1 it just
if they are all one
基本就是这个bit的符号扩展
yeah it basically just has to be a sign extension of this single bit
它们会被忽略
and then they're ignored otherwise
所以当你看到内核地址
so when you see kernel addresses
有内核地址吗
is there still a kernel address
这就是
here you have
当你看到这个内核地址FFF
and when you see this kernel address FFF
它是一个符号扩展后的48位地址
it's just a sign extended 48 bit address
48位外的都是0（口误）
where the top byte is 0
所以它是内核
so it's a kernel
首位是1（英文口误），所以是内核地址
a top bit is 0 so it's a kernel address
现在
now
如果前16位是混的
yes so if they're a mix
既有0，也有1
kind of as if they're a mix of zeros and ones
就会报段错误
you will end up with a segmentation fault
它不是一个合法的地址
it's not a valid address
但为什么我们不在那里放东西呢
but kind of saying why not let us store stuff there
某些平台可以
certain platforms do
这是ARM指针标签的原理
this is how arm pointer tagging and
我不知道英特尔是否在研发他们自己的指针标签
I don't know if intel is working on their own pointer tagging works
如果你查一下ARM指针标签
so if you look at arm pointer tagging
ARM内存标签扩展
arms memory tagging extensions
能让你出于安全目的，使用地址的高2字节
allow you to use the top byte for security storage
这个超级有用
which is super super useful
什么是ARM指针完整性
and what's the thing arm pointer integrity
PAC，指针访问控制
yes PAC exactly Pointer Access Control
所有这些都是聪明的安全解决方案
all of this stuff is clever security solutions
使用了指针中剩余的空闲位
that use slack space that's still left around in the pointers
你也可以放入加密的签名
so you can have like some sort of a cryptographic signature
你想放什么标签都可以
you can have whatever tag you want
我们上周刚有一篇论文被接收了
we just last week had a paper accepted
我们使用了ARM的高字节忽略功能
where we used Arm's top byte ignore feature
基本上就是在指针中存储对象id
to basically store object ids inside the pointers
就能在代码访问限制对象前，完成验证
so that we could validate them before code access objects that it wasn't supposed to access
实际上，对这些位的使用，的增多
actually the increasing use of this memory space or the the extra bits for
什么来着
what's it called
出于安全性的使用
for security
我猜这大概意味着
I'm guessing probably means that
我们不会用48位以上的可寻址内存了
we might never get to over 48 bits of addressable memory
希望不要马上打脸
please not easily
回到虚拟机隔离
so virtual machine isolation
这是疯狂的
it's insane
每个虚拟机都有自己的扩展页表
basically every virtual machine has its own extended page table
它是一个四层结构
which is a four level structure
有EPT PML4，EPT PDPT，EPT PD和EPT PT
it has an EPT PML4、EPT PDPT and EPT PD and EPT PT
它将客户机物理地址，转换成客户机虚拟地址（口误）
that handles the translation of guest physical addresses into guest virtual addresses
也就是说，你最后会得到
which means that you will end up with
对不起
sorry
将客户机物理地址，转成宿主机物理地址
guest physical addresses into host physical addresses
也就是说
which means that
会经过这个疯狂的二维查找过程
you have this insane two dimensional lookup process
最开始查找客户机的PML4
where you start looking up the PML4 of the guest
用客户机的EPT PML4
and you use the PML4 of the guest
从客户机的CR3找到的EPT PML4
from that CR3 register in the guest
查看客户机中CR3保存的物理地址
you look up the physical address in the guest the guest physical address stored in CR3
用一系列EPT指针，找到PML4
using the EPT pointers to figure out the PML4
找到宿主机中的PML4的物理地址
that PML4's physical address in the host
然后
and then you
用虚拟地址，查找下面要用的PDPT
you use the virtual address to look up the pdpt
客户机中的PDPT
the pdpt physical address in the guest
然后用EPT系列指针，找到宿主机中的PDPT
then resolve use the EPT to resolve that into its address in the host
这太疯狂了
and it's just insane
it's insane it's just crazy
好吧不管怎样
okay anyways
这要大量的查找
that's a lot of lookups
难道这不会很慢吗
isn't all of this slow as molasses
如果在内核里做这些的话，会很慢
well it would be if you're doing all of this inside the kernel
但实际上没有
but you don't actually
有专门的硬件
you have a specialized piece of hardware
称为内存管理单元
called the memory management unit
这些都是在硬件上完成的
that does all of this in hardware
速度非常快
and it's super fast
再用就更快了
and then it's even faster
因为只要它成功找到地址后
because whenever it successfully resolves something
它就将其存储在缓存中
it stores it in a cache
称为快表（TLB）
called the translation lookaside buffer
当然这意味着
of course this means that
这开放了缓存侧的攻击面
things become open to cache side channel attacks
等等等等
and etc etc etc
这在其他架构上是如何工作的
how does this work on other architectures
哦，抱歉，这应该，哦，没问题
oh sorry this is suppose to okay
其它架构上是怎样的
how does this work on other architectures
有点类似
kind of similarly
AMD和Intel在某个时候合作发明了
so AMD and Intel collaboratively at some point invented or
我记得是AMD为AMD64做了大量的工作
I think AMD did the bulk of this for AMD64
发明了这个4级页面表
invented this 4 level page table
ARM也有类似的东西
arm has something similar
你们可以去看看ARM的文档
you can go and actually read the arm documentation
但基本的思路是
but the basic idea
ARM上有等同于CR3的寄存器
there's a CR3 equivalent in arm of the
语气助词
fuck
叫 转换表 什么的 寄存器 0
the Translation Table something Register 0
它用于用户空间地址
for the user space addresses
一般来说，TTBR1用于内核空间地址
and typically the translation table something register 1 for kernel addresses
它们指向0级，还是3级
those points to a level 0 or level 3
我不记得哪一个是最大的
I don't remember which one is the the biggest
哪个是最小的转换表
which one is the smallest translation table
然后指向1、2、3级等等
which then point to level 1 2 3 etc etc
类似于PML4 PDPT PD和PT
and it's analogous to PML4 PDPT PD and PT
当然，Linux既可在x86，也可在arm上运行
of course Linux runs both on x86 and arm
所以它必须
so it has to
啊，BR代表基地址寄存器
ah base register
多谢，用户：反乌托邦
thank you dystopia
转换表基地址寄存器0
the Translation Table Base Register 0
转换表基地址寄存器1
Translation Table Base Register 1
Linux可以在所有这些架构上运行
Linux runs on all of these things
所以他们发明了一个通用术语
so they invented a generic terminology
这真的很愚蠢
which is really silly
因为很明显他们没料到第四级会出现
because obviously they didn't expect level 4 to show up I guess
但基本上有，页表
but basically there's the Page Table
然后是，页中层目录
then there's the Page Mid-level Directory
和页上级目录
and the Page Upper Directory
最后到第四级
and then they ended up getting a fourth level
他们说，好吧，比“上级”高的是什么
and they're like all right what's higher than upper
就叫 全局 吧
so they've been global
页面全局目录
page global directory
Linux实现了这些概念
Linux implement these concepts
但没实现内存查找和缓存之类的
but it doesn't implement the memory lookup and caching and stuff
它需要一个硬件MMU
it requires a hardware MMU
如果你疑惑过，为什么Linux不像Arduino
so if you ever wonder why Linux doesn't run unlike Arduino natively
至少是主流的Linux不像
at least mainline Linux
这就是为什么
that's why
但也有像uCLinux这样的Linux分支
but there are forks of Linux like uCLinux
不需要MMU
that do not require MMU
我为什么要告诉你这些疯狂的事
why am I telling you all of this insanity
我说这些
I'm telling you this
是因为
because
在内核中
by being in the kernel
你可以打破进程隔离
you can break process isolation
你可以用非常糟糕的方式破坏它
you can break it in real bad ways
如果你有代码执行
so if you have code execution
你的目标
your goal
以前
and it used to be that
你甚至不需要代码执行，来打破进程隔离
you didn't even need to have code execution to break process isolation
如果你是root
if you're a root
你可以打开/dev/mem
you could open /dev/mem
并直接访问物理内存
and literally directly access physical memory
这很有趣
and it was fun
你可以搜索内存
you could search around
你可以打开vim
you could open up vim
输入一些文字
and put in some text
然后在物理内存中搜索它
and then search for it in physical memory
就通过/dev/mem
by opening /dev/mem
这样的日子一去不复返了
those old days are gone
这是一个非常大的安全问题
that's a very big security no no
头脑正常的人都不会这么做
no one in their right mind would do that
/dev/mem仍然存在
/dev/mem still exists
能让你访问某些内存映射的硬件
to allow you to access certain memory map hardware
输入输出设备
input output devices
但它不再允许你访问物理内存
but it doesn't allow you to access physical memory
现在如果你想访问物理内存
now if you want to access physical memory
你必须是内核
you have to be the kernel
而你能成为内核
and you will be the kernel
因为你将在这整个模块中，实现内核中的代码执行
because you'll achieve code execution in the kernel throughout this module
内核有两个非常有用的宏
the kernel has two very useful macros that you can play around with
一个宏接受一个物理地址
one macro takes a physical address
并将其转换为内核虚拟地址
and converts it into a kernel virtual address
为什么这是可能的
why is this possible
因为内核映射了整个物理内存空间
because the kernel maps the entire physical memory space
你没有那么多的物理内存
you don't have that much physical memory
我有64 GB或者128 GB
I have 64 GBs or something or 128
这是
it's
不，这个有64GB
no this one has 64
所以我有64GB
so I have 64 GBs
有64个巨页
that's 64 huge pages
映射起来不难
it's not hard to map
所以你把它映射到
so you map it into
抱歉
excuse me a
内核内部的虚拟内存空间，以便于访问
into a virtual memory space inside the kernel for ease of access
内核是这样做的
the kernel does this
所以它可以转换物理地址
and thus it can convert between physical
从任何给定的物理地址，转成虚拟地址
from any given physical to a virtual address
然后还能让自己的虚拟内存在物理内存中保持连续
and then it also keeps its own virtual memory contiguous in physical memory
所以它也可以转换回来
so it can also convert back
给定一个内核虚拟地址
given a kernel virtual address
它可以返回用户空间虚拟地址
it can give you back the user space virtual address
它不能为非内核地址做这个
now it can't do that for non kernel addresses as a giant pain in the ass
我为CTF挑战实现了它
I've implemented it for CTF challenges
你需要实现你自己的内存查找
you have to basically implement your own memory lookup stuff
因为内核会像正常人一样，用MMU
because the kernel uses MMU like a reasonable person
它不需要自己解析这些
it doesn't need to parse these things manually
这些宏非常简单
these macros are super simple
实际上只是一个偏移
there's literally just an offset
他们说好的，嘿
where they say okay hey
对于vert_to_phys，它是这个地址减去0xffff...
it's this address minus 0xffff blah blah blah for vert_to_phys
对于phys_to_virt，它是加上0xf...
or plus 0xf blah blah for phys_to_virt